<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands concern in the case of His R.H.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4819</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12791772</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12791772</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93949</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38384)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93949)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 379:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands concern in the case of His R.H.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H.R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Concerns the repeal of the Test act and the penal laws.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93949:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93949:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ENGLANDS</hi> CONCERN IN THE CASE OF His R. H.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. R.</hi> in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93949:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93949:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ENGLANDS</hi> CONCERN IN THE <hi>Caſe of His R. H.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving ſeen and read all the Pamphlets for, and againſt the Power of Parliaments in the Right of Succeſſion, I cannot but conclude both Sides miſtaken in the Main, and to have, wilfully or ignorantly, paſt-over, or wrong ſtated, the Chief part of the Queſtion; which was, not what the Parliament, meaning King, Lords, and Commons, could do, by vertue of their Might or Power; but, What in Juſtice, or Prudence, they ought to do in the Caſe of His R. H?</p>
            <p>In the firſt Notion, no man in his wits can diſpute, that the ſtronger joyning againſt the weaker, have not power to do what they pleaſe: But this being a Right of Nature, to which both Parties are equally entituled, and both, upon entring into Society, have renounced or changed for an Artificial Right or Power, that of the Magiſtrate, or Community, cannot fall within the limits of the Queſtion; becauſe it can never be made uſe of, without running into a State of War, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an end to all Society, and, with <hi>Iſmael,</hi> having <hi>ones hand againſt every man, and every mans hand againſt him.</hi> And therefore in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Notion this Controverſie is to be taken, <hi>viz.</hi> What in Juſtice, by the Laws in being; or, ſince the Inſtance is extraordinary, What in Prudence, in Reaſon, the Parliament may do? For, this being the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Judicature, muſt not want a ſufficient Authority in any Caſe that can poſſibly happen.</p>
            <p>We muſt then inquire, Whether ſome Actions of the D. have been obnoxious and cenſurable? and, if found ſo, What is their proper or condign Puniſhment? In order to which, 'tis to be premiſed, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in its own nature is or can be Penal, or cenſurable <hi>in foro huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> but a Tranſgreſſion of ſome poſitive Inſtitution of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, or a Deviation from the Dictates of Right Reaſon. Now
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93949:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Crime objected, but never yet proved, nor conſeſſed, is the D's going over from the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church. This is the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe, that ruines our City; for in its Belly is hid a myſterious Conſequence, <hi>viz.</hi> That his doing ſo, gave encouragement, and was the occaſion of the late diſcovered Popiſh Plot. The firſt part of this Accuſation is a breach of the Laws of <hi>England;</hi> the latter, of thoſe of Reaſon, and all Nations; and therefore puniſhable after the moſt ſevere manner. But before Sentence, or Execution, 'tis to be obſerv'd. That not onely our own, but the Laws of all Countries, require not onely the Criminal's Conviction, but that his Sufferings be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurate to his Offence. This laſt muſt be known by the ſtated Meaſures, the Rules of the Society and Country; the former is built upon the ſame Foundation, and neceſſarily ſuppoſes a Legal Proceſs, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Evidence. Both are wanting in this of the D. he having never been ſummoned to appear, nor Witneſs produc'd to prove him guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For, who can ſay he has chang'd his Religion, or that, if he be now a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> he has not been ſo ever ſince he came to the uſe of Reaſon, ſince he was forced to fly, to avoid the Effects of the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion? If that be ſo, who are moſt in the fault, thoſe who occaſioned this Evil, or he that ſuffered himſelf, before his years enabled him to underſtand better, and to chuſe, to be perſuaded that was not the trueſt Religion, that authoriz'd ſuch Impieties as <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> forbids? If this be his Caſe, he is not liable to the Pains of Treaſon, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt the Perverters and Perverted to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion. But, to wave Diſputes, allowing it were otherwiſe, yet the Statute of General Pardon enacted in the year 1673 has ſo acquitted him from all guilt, that on this Foot he now ſtands <hi>rectus in curia,</hi> innocent before any Earthly Tribunal.</p>
            <p>But as to the Conſequence, That his being reconciled to <hi>Rome</hi> has given occaſion and Encouragement to the Plot, I can onely ſay, That he cannot in reaſon be blam'd on that account, if it be not proved he intended and deſigned that horrid Contrivance. 'Tis the End and Intention that juſtifies, or condemns any Action; and neither Father nor Mother are to be cenſured, that a Monſter happens to be the Iſſue of a Marriage-bed. This being accidental (for ſo it muſt be granted, till the contrary be made out) can no more be imputed to his R. H. without madneſs or folly, than it can to God, without Blaſphemy or Irreligion, That by his making Man he is the Authour and Cauſe of Sin, and all the Evils under Heaven.</p>
            <p>I am unwilling to mention what I have ſeen in Print, to wit, <hi>That the D. of York's being a Papiſt has given birth and life to the Plor;</hi> becauſe this is ſo, inartificial and illogical an Inference or Concluſion, that I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93949:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> am perſuaded the Authours will be aſhamed of the Ignorance or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice it betrays: An Aſſertion that has neither Sence, nor Wit, nor more force than the Old Wives Story, <hi>The Cat waſh'd her Face a Sunday, therefore it rain'd a Munday;</hi> or any other ſuch impertinent or ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Saying. Indeed, if this could be made appear, I think it a Crime of ſo foul a nature, that nothing leſs than Death, not Diſinheriſon, could ſatisfie the Juſtice of the Nation. But from this the D. is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted by Mr. <hi>Oates;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> even in his laſt words, clears him from having any knowledge of the Deſign againſt the King's Life; in which, and in the bringing in Religion by the Sword, (of which his R. H. is not accuſed) the Treaſon or Conſpiracy doth conſiſt. And being freed by theſe two, by whom elſe has he been accuſed? By Mr. <hi>Dangerfield.</hi> As to this, tell me what you think, when you reflect, that he gave in his Depoſitions to the late Lord Mayor, and to the King and Council, the firſt and ſeventh of <hi>November,</hi> 1679. and upon Oath declared, ſo often, he had nothing of further Diſcovery or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. What credit will you then give his late new Accuſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Houſe of Commons, of the D. Lord Privy-Seal, Earl of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terborough,</hi> and Lady <hi>Powis?</hi> Whatever the Infamy of his Perſon, and the former Actions of his Life would ſignifie, this alone, in my opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would invalidate his Teſtimony, in all matters, with Men of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or of Conſcience. So that upon the whole matter, from what does hitherto appear, the printed Narratives and Letters to and from Popes and Cardinals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I am not afraid to avow, That excluding the D. his Right of Succeſſion, is contrary to the Laws of God, and of this Kingdom (expreſſed in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and agreeable to thoſe that give every man his due, Liberty of Perſon, and Deſcent of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, and all the Advantages of Birthright; Bleſſings every Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man has in common with the Prince: and if the greater be thus out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; how ſhall the leſs be ſecured?) and to the Rules of Reaſon, which forbid the doing any Action that in its conſequence will be a greater Evil, than that from which we intended to be freed. The two firſt parts of this Aſſertion are very plain, becauſe Religion or Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alters not the Political Conſtitutions of any Society, and becauſe Popery in <hi>England</hi> hinders no man from being Heir to Real or Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eſtates; the third therefore is to be made evident, to wit, That Prudence and Reaſon tell us the D. ought not to be barr'd of Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I ſay then. This Act is not onely unjuſtifiabie at preſent, but in future and conſequence, as what will bring upon the whole Nation irreparable Miſchiefs. Where there are more hazards of an ill, than a good Event, the Action is in prudence to be avoided. In great and momentous Inſtances new Experiments are not to be tryed; nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93949:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> in any Caſe, or Diſtemper, where the Remedy is like to prove more fatal than the Diſeaſe. Now to give or allow ſo boundleſs, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary, and deſpotick a Power, as that of putting by the next Heir, or puniſhing <hi>ex poſt facto,</hi> either in the King alone, (who is obliged under the Obligations of Oaths and Intereſt to govern by the ſtated Meaſures of Law) or in him, when adviſing with both Houſes, (whoſe Power is ſo far from being co-ordinate or independent, that it is onely communicated, or derivative from the Prince, as Streams from the Fountain, and therefore can add or give him nothing new) is to ſubject and enſlave our ſelves and our Poſterities. For, if every one be a Papiſt, whom Faction or Malice, Preſumption or ſlight Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and no poſitive Proofs, have made ſo; and if the right Heir on this account, or for being really a Papiſt, may be deſpoiled of his Right by Parliament, ſince there can be greater Crimes or Evils than Popery, which we all acknowledge conſiſtent with Salvation, what can ſecure all future Princes, even the King at any time in being, from being laid aſide and dethron'd. To endeavour ſo abſolute a Subverſion of our Government, if it be not Treaſon, is to deſign, if it be purſued, that which cannot but happen, Anarchy and Confuſion, and all the Calamities of an unnatural Civil War.</p>
            <p>Againſt this, there is but one Objection, That in the notion of a Parliament a King is implied, and nothing can be ſuppoſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his own Ruine. This, I confeſs, is true in nature, in <hi>Theſt,</hi> but not in the fact <hi>in Hypotheſi:</hi> for, what has been once done, may be again: Tumults and Factions, Cunning and Addreſs, may make a Prince quit his Crown to ſave his Life; and yet none ever loſt the firſt, but ſoon after did the ſecond: nay, every Flower or Jewel he parts with, is a ſtep or advance to his Grave: And the Conſiderer of the <hi>Weighty Conſiderations</hi> leaves in this Objection no Force, by men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the Seconds of the <hi>Edwards</hi> and <hi>Richards</hi> depoſed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Authority; he might have added to his Catalogue the late Royal martyr'd <hi>CHARLES.</hi> While this Book, in many Paſſages trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, is publickly ſold before the Doors of Parliament, who can lay aſide fatal Apprehenſions; eſpecially when Two Houſes of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons have ſucceſſively prepared a Bill diſpoſing of the Crown con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the King's expreſs Commands; and former Preſidents? And becauſe I will not run to far back, and that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd for one of the beſt of our Princes, I will inſtance what in ſome great Points hapned in her Reign, concerning the Commons inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling in the Eccleſiaſtical and the Crown Affairs, their Right and her Prerogative.</p>
            <p>In the Twenty third year of her Reign, when the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93949:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt ordered to have a Time of Prayer and Humiliation appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in the Temple, on Sunday-fort'night after, the Queen hindred it, and ſent a Meſſage to the Houſe by Mr. Vice-Chamberlain, declaring, <hi>That her Highneſs had great admiration of the raſhneſs of this Houſe, in committing ſuch an apparent Contempt of her expreſs Command, as to put in execution ſuch an Innovation, without her privity, and pleaſure firſt known.</hi> And thereupon Mr. Vice-Chamberlain moved the Houſe to make humble Submiſſion to her Majeſty, acknowledging the ſaid Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Contempt, craving a Remiſſion of the ſame, with a full purpoſe to forbear the committing of the like hereafter. And by the conſent of the whole Houſe, Mr. Vice-Chamberlain carried their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to her Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe in the Twenty eighth year of her Reign, the Queen ſaid, <hi>She was ſorry the Commons medled with Chuſing and Returning Knights of the Shire for</hi> Norfolk, <hi>a thing impertinent for the Houſe to deal withal, and onely belonging to the Office and Charge of the Lord Chancellor, from whom the Writs iſſue, and are returned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Thirty ninth year of her Reign, the Commons, by their Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, complaining of Monopolies; the Queen made anſwer, by the the Lord Keeper, <hi>That ſhe hoped her dutiful and loving Subjects would not take away her Prerogative, which is the chiefeſt Flower in her Garland, and the principal and head Pearl in her Crown and Diadem; but that they will rather leave that to her diſpoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Thirty fifth year of her Reign, Mr. <hi>Peter Wentworth</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Bromley</hi> delivered a Petition to the Lord Keeper, deſiring the Lords of the Upper Houſe to be Suppliants with them of the Lower Houſe, unto her Majeſty, for Entailing the Succeſſion of the Crown, whereof they had a Bill ready drawn. Her Majeſty was highly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd herewith, as contrary to her former ſtrait Command, and charged the Council to draw the Parties before them. Sir <hi>Thomas Henage</hi> ſent for them, and commanded them to forbear the Parliament, and not to go out of their ſeveral Lodgings: After, they were called before the Lord Treaſurer, the Lord <hi>Buckhurſt,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Henage;</hi> Mr. <hi>Wentworth</hi> was committed by them to the Tower; Sir <hi>Henry Bromley,</hi> and other Members of the Houſe of Commons, to whom he imparted the Matter, were ſent to the <hi>Fleet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the ſame Parliament, when Mr. <hi>Morriee,</hi> Attorney of the Court of Wards, moved againſt the hard Courſes of the Biſhops, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarles, and other Eccleſiaſtical Judges, in their Courts, and ſpake againſt Subſcriptions and Oaths, offering a Bill to be read againſt Impriſonment for refuſal of Oaths; the ſame afternoon Sir <hi>Edward Coke,</hi> then Speaker, was ſent for to Court, where the Queen her ſelf
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93949:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> gave him a Meſſage to the Houſe, declaring, <hi>It being wholly in her power to call, to determine, to aſſent or diſſent to any thing done in Parliament; That the calling of this was onely that the Majeſty of God might be more Religiouſly obſerved, by compelling, by ſome ſharp Laws, ſuch as neglect that Service; and that the Safety of her Majeſties Perſon, and the Realm, might be provided for: It was not meant they ſhould meddle with Matters of State, or Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical; and ſhe wondred that any could be of ſo high commandment, to attempt a thing ſo expreſly contrary to that which ſhe had commanded; wherefore with this ſhe was highly offended: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Words ſpoken by my Lord Keeper are not now perhaps well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, or ſome be now here that were not then preſent; her Majeſties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Charge, and expreſs Command, is, That no Bill touching the ſaid Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of State, or Reformation in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, be exhibited: And upon my Allegiance</hi> (ſaith the Speaker) <hi>I am charged, if any ſuch Bill be exhibited, not to read it.</hi> I have been credibly informed, That the Queen ſent a Meſſenger, or Serjeant at Arms, into the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and took out Mr. <hi>Morrice,</hi> and committed him to Priſon. Within few days after, I find Mr. <hi>Wroth</hi> moved in the Houſe, That they might be humble Suitors to her Majeſty, that ſhe would be pleas'd to ſet at liberty thoſe Members of the Houſe that were reſtrained; which was accordingly done: And anſwer was ſent them by her Privy-Council, <hi>That her Majeſty had committed them for Cauſes beſt known to her ſelf; and to preſs her Highneſs with this Suit, would but hinder them whoſe good they ſought: That the Houſe muſt not call the Queen to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for what ſhe doth of her Royal Authority: That the Cauſes for which they are reſtrained, may be high and dangerous: That her Majeſty liketh no ſuch Queſtions, neither doth it become the Houſe to ſearch into Matters of that nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In 39 <hi>Eliz.</hi> the Commons were told, <hi>Their Privilege was</hi> Yea <hi>and</hi> No: <hi>And that her Majeſties pleaſure was, That if the Speaker perceived any idle Heads, which would not ſtick to hazard their own Eſtates, but meddle with reforming the Church, and transforming the Commonweal, by exhibiting Bills to that purpoſe, the Speaker ſhould not receive them, till they were view'd and conſider'd by thoſe, who are fitter to conſider of ſuch things, and can better judge of them.</hi> And at the end of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Queen rejected Forty eight Bills, which had paſſed both Houſes. All theſe Paſſages are expreſly to be found in the Records and Regiſtries of the Council-Table, and are quoted by Sir <hi>Robert Filmer,</hi> in his <hi>Free holders Grand Inqueſt,</hi> p. 77, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by Mr. <hi>Howel,</hi> ſometimes Clerk of the Council, in his <hi>Philanglus,</hi> p. 57, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others.</p>
            <p>By which it appears, That this grand Privilege of Parliament,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93949:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Liberty of Speech,</hi> which at preſent makes ſo great a Noiſe in the World, was not, in this good Queens Reign, half ſo conſiderable as People now would fain perſuade us. It was of no great antiquity in her days, but a Favour firſt begged in King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Reign, by Sir <hi>Thomas Moore,</hi> then Speaker of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who prayed the King, in the behalf of the Houſe, <hi>That if in Communication and Reaſoning any man ſhould ſpeak more largely than of duty he ought to do, that all ſuch Offences ſhould be pardoned, and this to be entred upon Record:</hi> which was accordingly granted by the King. And the ſame Favour was allowed by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her Reign, to <hi>Thomas Gargrave,</hi> then Speaker: ſince whoſe time this Privilege was always humbly deſired by the Speakers, for themſelves, and the whole Houſe of Commons, and favourably gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their Sovereign. Yet this Privilege extended onely to raſh, unadviſed, ignorant, or negligent Eſcapes, and Slips in Speech, which People are ſubject to let fall in the heat of their Debates; not to wilful Reflections, much leſs to treaſonable Speeches, againſt the King and Government: as ſufficiently appears, not onely by the aforeſaid Proceedings in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> time, but alſo by the Tranſactions of her Father's Reign, where we find, that <hi>Richard Strood</hi> and his Complices were not thought ſufficiently protected by this Privilege for their free Speech in the Houſe, unleſs their Pardon were expreſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the King in Parliament: to which purpoſe there is a printed Statute enacted in King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's time. And in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry's</hi> days, <hi>Plowden</hi> was Fin'd in the <hi>King's Bench,</hi> for Words ſpoken by him in <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the Queen's Dignity. See <hi>Filmer ubi ſupra.</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Fowlis Hiſt. of the Plots &amp; Conſpiracies of the Pretended Saints,</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>This was well known to our <hi>Britiſh Solomon</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> who finding the Houſe of Commons encroaching too far upon the Prerogative, ſent the enſuing Letter from <hi>Newmarket,</hi> to Sir <hi>Thomas Richardſon</hi> their Speaker. <hi>Mr. Speaker, We have heard, to our grief, That our diſtance from the Parliament, cauſed by our indiſpoſition of Health, hath emboldned ſome fiery and popular Spirits of the Lower Houſe to debate Matters above their Capacity, to our Diſhonour, and breach of Prerogative Royal. Theſe are therefore to command you to make known to them, That none hereafter ſhall preſume to medle with any thing concerning our Government, or Matters of State; with our Sons Match with the Daughter of</hi> Spain, <hi>nor to touch the Honour of that King, or any other our Friends or Confederates, nor with any Mans Particulars, which have their due Motion in our ordinary Courts of Juſtice. And whereas they have ſent a Meſſage to Sir</hi> Edwin Sandis, <hi>to know the Reaſons of his late Reſtraint; you ſhall reſolve them, It was not for any Miſdemeanour of his in Parliament: But to put them out of</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:93949:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>doubt of any Queſtion hereafter of that nature, We think our ſelf very free and able to puniſh any Mans Miſdemeanours in Parliament, as well ſitting there, as after; which we mean not to ſpare hereafter, upon any Occaſion of any Mans. And if they have touch'd any Point, which We have here forbidden, in any Petition of theirs, which is to be ſent to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, tell them, (except they reform it) We will not daign the Hearing or Anſwering.</hi> Newmarket, <hi>Decemb.</hi> 3. 1621. Sanderſon's <hi>Hiſtory of King</hi> James, <hi>pag.</hi> 510.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe, in the ſame Parliament, when the Houſe of Commons much inſiſted upon their Privileges, calling them <hi>their ancient and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Inheritance,</hi> this wiſe Prince, in a ſecond Letter to the Speaker, plainly and truly told them, <hi>That moſt Privileges of Parliament grew from Precedents. which ſhews rather a Toleration, than an Inheritance; therefore he could not allow of the Style, calling it their ancient and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Right and Inheritance; but could rather have wiſhed that they had ſaid, their Privileges were derived from the Grace and Permiſſion of his Anceſtors and him.</hi> And thereupon he concludes, <hi>He cannot with patience endure his Subjects to uſe ſuch Antimonarchical Words concerning their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, except they had ſubjoyned, That they were granted unto them by the Grace and Favour of his Predeceſſors:</hi> Yet he promiſeth <hi>to be careful of whatſoever Privileges they enjoyed by long Cuſtom, and uncontrolled and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Precedents,</hi> Sanderſon's Hiſt. p. 519. &amp; 520.</p>
            <p>Now, add to this, That if the King ſhould be drawn to conſent to the Bill of Excluſion, after his ſeveral Declarations to the contrary, he cannot but be concluded under a Conſtraint, which alone makes the Act void in it ſelf; it being abſolutely neceſſary, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Lords, and the Kings Conſent ſhould be free from all Reſtraint and Terrour: and we know, that Acts of Parliament in 15 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and 10 <hi>Ric</hi> 2. were repealed, meerly becauſe the King's Conſent was forced.—Moreover, if we ſeriouſly did conſider the mighty Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of an Hereditary Monarchy beyond an Elective, we ſhould find it reaſonable, that though the Laws had not, yet the King ſhould, endeavour to make ours ſuch; much leſs ought he to alter that moſt happy Conſtitution, by excluding his Brother. For, let Men ſay what they pleaſe, the ſame Power that can put by One, may All; and ſo change the Beſt of Government for the Worſt, or None at all.</p>
            <p>Beſides, His Majeſty cannot but find it his own Intereſt to ſtick to the D. when he reflects, that there is in all things, eſpecially in State-Affairs, a Balance neceſſary, by an equal Libration to keep things in a right Order, and prevent Confuſion and Ruine. Where Men are, there will be Ambition; this creates Parties and Factions; theſe muſt be kept divided, and aſunder; by their Jars and Diſagreement, and by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93949:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo poiſing them, that the leſs, like the ſmaller Fry of Fiſhes, be not ſwallowed by the greater, the ſafety of the Prince and State is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd. If the Prince be once prevail'd upon to joyn with the One, to the ſuppreſſion of the Other, he has reſigned his Power, and expoſed himſelf to the Mercy of the Conqueror. This he likewiſe does, if he gives way to ſeveral little Factions to embody into one of greater ſtrength than the reſt, though aſſiſted with that of his own Particular: For here we muſt ſuppoſe three ſtrong Parties, one of the Prince, and two of the People. To keep this Balance in the beſt poſture, and to ſecure the Peace of the Commonwealth, by the Kings reigning void of Fear or Jealouſie on the ſcore of Factions, or his Succeſſor, 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in politie to find or make the next Heir the Object of the Peoples hatred, and keep the Factions from combining; becauſe, however they may chance to be weary of the King, either through the inconſtancy of their Humours, ſtudious of Change and Variety, though for the worſe, or through the ill Conduct of Miniſters, or the Misfortunes of Publick Affairs; when they find a Perſon whom they hate like to ſucceed, they will be for continuance of the old; or elſe, being jealous of one another, will not attempt his removal. This then being ſo great an advantage, prudent Kings cannot be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to neglect it, by ſuffering the immediate Heir to be run down, and thereby giving way to the People to dethrone the preſent Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor, and ſet up the next in courſe after. To this Wiſdom in <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, gain'd by his own and Fathers Misfortunes, we owe our preſent Conſtitution of Parliament. This King perceiving the Lords Power (in whom, with himſelf, the Supreme Legiſlative Right then conſiſted) grown formidable, the Commons being their Livery-men and Dependents, erected theſe into a Lower Houſe, to counterpoiſe the weight of the other, that he joyning with either, as Occaſion of State required, might balance the other, and ſo keep things in an equal and ſteddy Libration. And if his Succeſſors had been as ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous to maintain, as he was to inſtitute, this good Order and Politie, the Eternity of this Commonwealth would not at this day have been a Queſtion. And as this was our Home-Intereſt, and that of hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scales even between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> our Foreign; ſo it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears, that not to exclude the Duke, is not onely his Majeſties particular Intereſt, but alſo that of the Three Kingdoms. Not to inſiſt, that the Parliament is not compleatly the Peoples Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, but granting it is, they cannot be ſuppoſed to enjoy a greater Power than thoſe they repreſent; who, becauſe ſuch, are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and therefore muſt be concluded, explicitly or implicitly, to limit the Commiſſions of theſe their Truſtees; and that Conſinement, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93949:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> will tell us, muſt be within the Bounds of our ancient Rights and Privileges; conſequently, theſe are not to be invaded, without the conſent of every individual Perſon, or at leaſt of the major part, truly poll'd and computed. The preſent Electors, not making a ſixth part of the Nation, cannot in reaſon bind the reſt, contrary to their Intereſt; much leſs can the Majority of thoſe, choſen by them, oblige the others to conform to whatever they enact, when they find the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes more prejudicial than advantageous; the End of Government being the Good of the Community, <hi>i. e.</hi> of the major part, not of any artificial or fictitious Majority of a <hi>Quorum,</hi> as in the Houſe of Commons, of 512 to reckon 40 the greater Number.</p>
            <p>Now if ſuch an Act ſhould be obtain'd, the Conſequence, if the D. ſurvive the King, <hi>(whoſe Life God long continue)</hi> muſt needs be War and Miſery, Folly and Repentance. Our Hiſtories are full of Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Events upon ſuch Occaſions: One of them wrought ſo great a Depopulation, that in ſixty miles riding, between <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Durham,</hi> for nine years together, there was neither Ground tilled, nor Houſe left ſtanding. <hi>Harold</hi> juſtling young <hi>Edgar Atheling</hi> out of the Throne, produced a Civil War, and the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt. I wiſh excluding the D. may not enſlave us to the <hi>French</hi> Dominion, which may be of greater evil, than the cutting of as many of our own Peoples Throats as died in the <hi>Yorkiſt</hi> and <hi>Lancaſtrian</hi> Quarrel, upwards of 200000 of the Commons, beſides ſeveral Kings and Princes, and Nobles with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number. The Duke cannot be ſuppoſed to want Sticklers both at home, and from abroad; few will believe the Act lawful in its own nature, nor the King's Conſent free, or themſelves not bound by Oath to his Aſſiſtance: <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> will rejoyce at another Civil War in <hi>England,</hi> in hopes to free themſelves from the Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of being Provinces. Thoſe who have leaſt to loſe, are the uſual Gainers by Rebellion. There are ſown between theſe Nations Seeds of Diſcontent, and there will not be wanting thoſe who will improve them. I have heard from knowing Perſons, there are no leſs than Fifty thouſand <hi>Iriſh</hi> Soldiers now living, that have been trained up in the <hi>French,</hi> and other Forreign Service; and I believe there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be fewer of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> People. Theſe all, with many of our own Countreymen, will quickly credit the Lawyers, that tell us, <hi>No Act, no Crime, no Attainder of Treaſon, can bar the next of Blood from being King in the inſtant of time his Predcceſſor does not ſo much die, as tranſmit his Life, his Breath, or his Soul, by a State-Metempſychoſis, into the Noſtrils, the Body of his Succeſſor. Edward</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> enjoy'd the Crown, though all excluded by Acts of Parliament, if they ought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93949:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> to have the name, that were the Effects of Force, Strong hand, and an uſurping Tyrannick Power. Theſe Statutes were by all Judges of <hi>England</hi> accounted void in themſelves, and therefore never had the honour of Repeals, nor were they brought into Plea by Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> one of the greateſt Wits of that Age, though he urged a very trivial one, <hi>The King's not being Crown'd;</hi> a Ceremony of Pomp and State, not of Uſe or Neceſſity, as appears not onely in that it could be of no uſe to him, but that ſeveral Kings have exerciſed a full Regal Authority, enacted Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> before their Coronations. And ſince this Inauguration is but a Formality, let it be well weigh'd, That unleſs the Monarchy be made purely Elective, and that part of the Common Law, and the ſeveral Statutes that have declared it Hereditary, be repealed in expreſs Words, and the Oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and Supremacy changed, and the Succeſſor mentioned by Name, the Act againſt the Duke falls to the ground of it ſelf, in the moment in which he happens to out-live the King; for thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming our lawful Sovereign, none can fight againſt, or oppoſe his Right to the Crown, without Perjury and Rebellion; we having ſworn to defend, againſt all Pretenders whatſoever, Forreign or Domeſtick, the King's Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors, and all Rights, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, and Preheminences to them belonging, and ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xed to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Crown of this Realm. And is not the Deſcent of the Crown upon the next of Blood one of theſe Rights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> acknowledged by the Common Law, and in the Statutes 1 <hi>M. Eliz. &amp; Jac.</hi> The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xim in our Laws, <hi>The King never dies,</hi> confirming as much. And was not the Duke then, at the taking of theſe Oaths, the next Heir? And what Power on Earth can abſolve from the Obligation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſory Oaths, without the Parties own Conſent to whom the Promiſe is made? Let us not rail againſt the Pope, for depoſing Princes, and abſolving Subjects from their Allegiance, and yet allow the Parliament the ſame Authority.</p>
            <p>The Bill againſt the Duke is not onely of an extraordinary, but of two natures; one expreſſes a preſent Puniſhment, Exile, which, as a Subject, did the Crime deſerve it, none will deny may be inflicted; the other refers to the future, and is at preſent no Puniſhment, nor can be hereafter; for if he out-live his Brother, his being King in that moment puts upon him a new Perſon, a Politick Capacity, over which, not before in being, no former Authority could have power, nor any after, becauſe himſelf is become Supreme, and, as ſuch, by our own, and the Laws of God, ſubject to no Earthly Tribunal. <hi>Bracton,</hi> and all our old honeſt Lawyers, tell us with one conſent, <hi>The King can do no wrong,</hi> i. e. can be accountable to his Subjects for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93949:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> none of his Actions. <hi>Nemo quidem de factis ejus praeſumat diſputare, multo minus contra factum ejus ire—Locus erit ſupplicationi, quod fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſuum corrigat &amp; emendet; quod quidem ſi non fecerit, ſufficit ei ad poenam, quod dominum Deum expectet ultorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now he that ſays, <hi>The Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy reach no further than to the King in being,</hi> ſays not amiſs, if he takes the King in his Publick Capacity; for, <hi>in that he never dies.</hi> But if he means no more than the Perſon of the now reigning Monarch, he cancels with his Death the Obligation of thoſe Oaths, and makes Rebellion againſt the Succeſſor no Crime againſt Conſcience, though it may be otherwiſe againſt Prudence. This is to elude the Oath, and rob it of the energy deſigned. For, 'tis plain by the Words <hi>Heirs and Succeſſors,</hi> that the Takers Obligation continues during their own Lives, let the Perſons of never ſo many Princes be alter'd; and as certain, that in an Hereditary Monarchy the Duty is owing to the next of Blood: And, that a Parliament, or any Power, may diſpence or abſolve from the Obligations eſpecially of Promiſſory Oaths, between Party and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without mutual conſent, is a Doctrine inconſiſtent with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Promiſes (where the Promiſer gives the other a Right, and makes himſelf his Debtor), with the Rules of Chriſtianity, of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society, and all Governments. 'Tis no leſs dangerous to aſſert, <hi>That Promiſſory Oaths, or Oaths</hi> de futuro, <hi>are not Obligatory.</hi> Such a Principle cancels all the Duties and Bonds of Obedience between Prince and Subject; of which therefore not onely the Divines, and my Lords the Biſhops, but the State, is to be very tender and careful. Upon this Foundation, 'tis evident, that if the Duke outlives his Brother, and the Monarchy of <hi>England,</hi> as it is, be Hereditary, and Coronation but Formality, we become upon the death of the one, the Subjects of the other: And though there may be ſome that will not think of this Truth, or notwithſtanding will not mind it; yet I am aſſur'd, all that are truly Chriſtians, and all that are of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and wiſe, will lay it to heart; for Chriſtianity, teaches, be the Prince of any, or no Religion, we muſt be obedient, and ſubmit our ſelves, <hi>not onely for wrath, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> In the late Times of Uſurpation they were ſo ſenſible of this, that they made the People Covenant againſt the King, and renounce their former by after Oaths; yet they durſt not depend on that Artifice, without the aſſiſtance of an Army. Thus then we ſee the Duke can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want a Party in <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Strength muſt over-power any other, when to it is united that of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And here let none be miſtaken, as if <hi>Scotland</hi> were govern'd or influenc'd by Presbyterian <hi>Domine</hi>'s; the Nobility there do wholly ſway, and hate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93949:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> refin'd Presbytery, and a Plebeian Commonwealth. Neither will the <hi>Scots</hi> be more forward to aſſiſt the Duke, than the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> in hopes they may thereby find an opportunity to extirpate the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and regain their ancient Poſſeſſions, free themſelves from any Dependence, or at leaſt change their preſent from that of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> which on many ſcores ſeems to be the true Intereſt of that Kingdom, politickly conſider'd, either as Popiſh or Proteſtant, without reſpect to Religion. 'Tis a ready In-let to <hi>France,</hi> who will not be wanting to aſſiſt the Duke in this Quarrel; the onely way he can hope, by gaining <hi>England</hi> on his ſide, to win the Univerſal Dominion. Now to reſiſt the Duke, an Army muſt be maintain'd; the General of that Army may turn Papiſt, or Tyrant, or both; and either way we may be enſlav'd: by the Duke, if he gains the Victory; or, if he loſes it, by our own Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. Thus we may, by ſhunning one Rock, ſplit upon another. The <hi>Romans</hi> deſigning to free themſelves from the ſeeming Tyranny of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> (who ſtudied by Clemency and Obligations upon every body to ſecure himſelf, as muſt needs be his R. H's Intereſt, as it is his Temper and Inclination) made way for the real and perpetual one, in the Perſons of <hi>Auguſtus, Tiberius,</hi> and their Succeſſors. And the <hi>Graecians</hi> repining againſt their lawful Emperors, and deeming their juſt and wholeſom Commands tyrannical and oppreſſive, were ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory, and ſo obſtinate, that, through ſpite to their Sovereign, they would contribute nothing towards the neceſſary Defence of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, when invaded by the <hi>Turk,</hi> until at laſt, through the juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Almighty, (a fitting Puniſhment for their Folly) they became a Prey to that Tyrant, and to this day continue the verieſt Slaves in Nature.</p>
            <p>And, I pray, why muſt we run all this hazard to ſecure Religion? If that be the thing, it may certainly be done by binding up the hands of a Popiſh Succeſſor by ſuch Laws as will make it Felony or Treaſon for a Papiſt to appear at Court, or bear any Office, and put it out of the Princes power to pardon ſuch Offences or Offenders. For my own part, I ſee no cauſe to apprehend a Popiſh Succeſſor, eſpecially the Duke, would or could alter our Laws or Religion. To attempt it, would be, for a Crown of Flowers, to forfeit one of Gold and Jewels. Has he ever offer'd to perſuade any of his Children, or his Servants, to change their Opinions? And why ſhould we think a Man who has never broken his Word or Promiſe, and ever profeſſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a Liberty of Conſcience, ſo reſtrain'd as might be conſiſtent with Publick Peace, ſhould, with his Fortune, alter his Judgment, contrary to Prudence, and contrary to his Intereſt? Kings are not now adays Prieſt-ridden; and the King of <hi>England</hi> cannot be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93949:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuppoſed to deſtroy his Subjects at their deſires, more than the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and other Princes of that Religion, where Non-Papiſts, or Proteſtants, live under the Protection of Laws, and enjoy their Liberties, and their Fortunes. Beſides, to offer by force to reduce all to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> would be Folly and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Neither the Conſtitution of <hi>England,</hi> nor Chriſtianity, will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of propagating Religion by the Sword. The next King, not to mention that his Subjects in the Three Kingdoms will be above Two hundred Proteſtants for One Papiſt, will not have the Fourth part of the preſent King's Revenue; which being inſufficient for the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Expences of the Crown, will neceſſitate him to have recourſe to, and compliance with his People in Parliament.</p>
            <p>But now conſider the Iſſue: If it pleaſe God, after this Bill paſs'd, in ſome ſhort time to take the King to himſelf, the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> perhaps in complement to her Father, and to prevent a War, may refuſe; and her Husband cannot come to the Throne, if ſhe decline it, others being before him. What then? the next after cannot come in; muſt the Duke then? No, that's againſt Law. Here will then be no King; conſequently, Anarchy and Confuſion. But if the Princeſs do aſſume the Crown, and after that the Duke have a Son, and he bred up in the Proteſtant Religion, what will then follow? Still a War. The Princeſs will be unwilling to reſign, and yet the other is moſt certainly King. But if this young Prince ſhould, during his Fathers Life, or his Siſters, be kept out; he, or his Iſſue after, contending with that of the Princeſs, will entail a War upon the Nations. So that upon the whole, if the Duke out-live the King, I ſee nothing but Miſery and Deſolation like to enſue upon his Diſinheriſon. And therefore I ſay, 'tis fitter to wave the Act wholly, or endeavour, by proving him guilty of the Plot by ſufficient Teſtimonies, to take away his Life. For, if we cannot be ſafe if he ſucceed, I am ſure we cannot, if he out-live our preſent Sovereign: a Bill of Attainder will be of no force; the beſt Lawyers will tell you, the Deſcent of the Crown waſhes that Stain away. A Project of <hi>Divorce</hi> whiſper'd between the King and Queen, will not be ſufficient Security: for, if that ſhould take, which is not probable, becauſe Chriſtianity forbids it; yet it's poſſible the King may have no Iſſue by a new Conſort; or, if he have, that the moſt will look on them but as Illegitimate: and ſo, as a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable <hi>Divorce</hi> once brought us from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's days, another may return us thither, during, or ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Reign of <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>And here I would have it remembred, That the Nature of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments requires their intermedling onely with what the King ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93949:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> or approve: He calls them to adviſe and deliberate as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, not to impoſe upon him in any Particular. Let therefore the Spirit of Moderation govern and direct their Counſels, put an end to the Plot, by trying the Accuſed. It has loſt <hi>England</hi> in its Trade already Six Millions, as has been lately computed by knowing Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; encreaſed our Jealouſies and Fears at home, made us a Scorn and Reproach abroad, and expoſed us to be a Prey to the Deſigns of Forreigners. Let not the Ambition, Malice, or Revenge of any of our Fellow-Subjects prevail to the enſlaving our ſelves and our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. If the Power of the Commons grow exorbitant, the Lords are with the King to counterpoiſe it, to prevent the otherwiſe not avoidable Ruine of the Commonwealth. To the Lords then this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs is humbly ſubmitted, praying they would betimes conſider all the fatal Conſequences of the Bill of Excluſion. The love of Truth and Juſtice, Courage, and the practice of thoſe Vertues in this great Affair, are the onely Preſervatives of <hi>Englands</hi> preſent Peace and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Happineſs. <hi>Faelix quem faciunt aliena pericula cautum.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what's paſt, and then I ſhall not need to add more than this,—. <hi>Verbum ſapienti.</hi> As for others, guided or miſled by Ignorance, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, or Intereſt, I can onely ſay, with the Poet,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid cum illis agas, qui neque jus, neque bonum atque aequum ſciunt? Melius, pejus, proſit, obſit; nihil vident, niſi quod lubet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I leave them to Time for a better Temper, to the Conduct of their own Reaſon, and God's Providence, for the Cure of their Folly, and for a better Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since I finiſh'd this Diſcourſe, the following Letter came to my hands; and believing it as advantageous to the Publick, as it is Ingenious, I have reſolved to add it, that thoſe who might repent the Charge of the former, may be recompenced by the latter.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I am griev'd at my very Soul, and infinitely aſham'd, to find by your laſt, that any make the Suppoſition of the D's being a Papiſt, and conſequently unfit to Govern, the pretence of running ſo high againſt the Monarchy; and, that ſo many are drawn into this violent Courſe and Faction, upon the ſurmiſe of his being, if once offended, irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall, in few words, return you my Opinion on theſe two Points. I cannot indeed but look on both as meer Artifices of ambitious Men,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93949:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> who, miſſing a ſhare in the preſent Conſtitution, contrive another Government, I wiſh I had not too much cauſe to ſay, It will at laſt end in a Commonwealth: For, if nothing were in their Heads, but ſecuring the Eſtabliſh'd Religion, they would not oppoſe Popery alone, but Presbytery, equally with the other deſtructive of That, for which they do not onely open a gap, but for the Opinions of all other Sectaries. And we cannot here but obſerve, with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with Reſolutions, which have put us upon Preparations, of ſticking by our Sovereign, againſt all manner of inſolent and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practices whatſoever, That the Commons have not brought any one Man into trouble, beſides Papiſts, but Men of known Loyalty, and of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Addreſſing, by repeated Inſtances, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of <hi>H.</hi> who ought, in our opinion, to have been executed for Treaſon, if guilty of no other Crime than his ſaying <hi>he could be back'd with Sixty thouſand Men,</hi> to ſtand by him for printing that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Libel, <hi>The Appeal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How is Popery more dangerous than Presbytery, either in Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or Practice? Suppoſe the firſt is for the King killing and Depoſing Doctrine, of which all her Profeſſors are aſham'd, and therefore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own it as a general Tenet, allowing it onely a probable Opinion of ſome private Divines: And where have Princes felt the Effects of it, as they have in <hi>Germany,</hi> from the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> from the <hi>Hugonots;</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> from the <hi>Geuſes;</hi> in <hi>Geneva, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> from the <hi>Presbyterians? For ſhame let's give the Devil his due, and not make him blacker than he is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Twas the Presbyterians of <hi>Scotland</hi> that made War againſt, and baniſh'd their lawful Queen <hi>M.</hi> and began the Rebellion in 37. againſt King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt. 'Twas theſe in <hi>England,</hi> and not the Papiſts, who fought in his defence, that cut off this Princes Head.</p>
                  <p>But what if the Papiſts ſay, <hi>An Heretick King may be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and depos'd, and that every one is ſo, that is not of the Church of Rome?</hi> Does not the Presbyterian ſay the ſame in other words? And is not the dogmatical Claſſis, or Synod, the ſole Arbitrator, and as Imperious and Infallible as St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair, <hi>That Dominion is founded in Grace?</hi> and, <hi>That an Idolatrous King may be cut off?</hi> and, <hi>That a King is but the Peoples Officer or Truſtee; and if he fails in his Duty, of which they alone are to be Judges, they may reſume their Grant, and ſpurn him beſide the Throne?</hi> Put one anent the other, <hi>the Hares Head againſt the Gooſe Giblets,</hi> and <hi>Dee'l a Barrel better Herring will you find among all.</hi> The Caſe is ſo plain, I need not inſtance Authors, eſpecially in a private Epiſtle: But let me ſee whether <hi>Knox</hi> or <hi>Buchanan</hi>'s Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, or any of your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyter Followers, can purge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93949:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> and their Writings, from theſe pernicious Principles. Did not all the Popiſh Plotters lately executed, not onely aver their own Innocence, but deny the King-killing Doctrine? Was not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary plain here with us, in the ſeveral Riſings of the <hi>Whigs?</hi> And did not the Murderers of the Archbiſhop of <hi>St. Andrews,</hi> as well as thoſe juſt now by-paſt, maintain the lawfulneſs of their Proceedings, and chuſe to die, aſſerting the King was juſtly excommunicate, and that it was doing God ſervice to kill him, rather than take their Pardon, and diſown thoſe damnable Tenets, and Doctrines of Devils? What a ſtir, all over your Nation, has the Murther of a ſingle Juſtice of Peace, Sir <hi>E. B. G.</hi> made? and even that, by the Papiſts, is not ſo very clear, but that ſome doubt whether they were really the Authors: But granting they were, thoſe that ſuffer'd for the Crime denied it, with horrid Execrations, and Aſſeverations of their Innocence; and yet allowing them guilty, that is much, very much, leſs than the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Aſſaſſination of a Proteſtant, the Metropolitan of <hi>Scotland;</hi> the wicked Inſtruments of which, the Presbyterians, were ſo far from diſowing it, that they impudently gloried in that inhumane Act, as a meritorious piece of Zeal and Devotion. And is it not a ſmaller Guilt or Evil, with the Papiſts, to deſign the killing of a King, than, with the Presbyterians, to have actually murder'd one of the beſt that ever ſway'd a Scepter; and, with thoſe Antichriſtian Zealots of this Kingdom, of the ſame Herd, to avow they would likewiſe gladly ſacrifice our preſent Sovereign? And yet what Prints or Pulpits have ſince inveigh'd againſt ſuch Helliſh Proceedings? Was not this, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a form'd Rebellion of many thouſands in the Field, huſh'd and paſs'd over in very few days, without noiſe, wonder, or abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? the Memory and Reproach of the other being ſtill in the Mouths of all, and freſheſt in theirs, who were Partizans, or of the ſame Principles with thoſe of our Villany. Away, away, Man, for ſhame; let it not be ſaid, that the Presbyterians are not ee'n as black as the Papiſts: Suppreſs both, or neither: 'Tis beſt policy to ſet them anent each other, for a Balance. If I did not hear, from all hands, the Inſolence of the Presbyterians; and with trouble read many of the Printed Votes, and the Ballads on the Biſhops, for voting againſt the D's Excluſion, I ſhould believe, that your preſent Fears and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders in <hi>England</hi> did proceed from apprehenſions of Popery; but by many Arguments I am convinc'd, That the D's private Opinion is but made the Stale to wreak their Malice againſt the Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and that Paſſion, more than Reaſon, does influence your Countrymen.</p>
                  <p>For, I pray conſider; Is not Faith the Gift of God? Can any Man
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93949:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> believe what he pleaſes? And who knows whether the D. was ever of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Did not the late Rebellion force him to fly into a Popiſh Country, in his Youth? And is it not next to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to remove Prepoſſeſſions, eſpecially conſidering the Unity, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, and Univerſality of that Church, wherein all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Divines allow Salvation? Can any Man change his Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, alter the figure of his Face, the ſtature of his Body, the colour of his Hair, or of his Skin? Is not the Jaundice a Diſeaſe in the Eye, that needs the help of Phyſick? And is not Errour, or Weakneſs in the Underſtanding, a Diſtemper alſo that requires the Aſſiſtance of a Phyſician? And what Remedy can be proper, but gentle Arguments, and the perſuaſive Arts of Diſcourſe, and ſober Reaſonings? Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution makes ſome Men, thoſe of great Souls, obſtinate; and others, of little, Hypocrites. But what Law enacts, That an Opinion, in the diſputable Parts of Religion, ought to deprive a Man of his Right to Inherit? Wou'd any of your Phanaticks (I am ſure none of our <hi>Whigs</hi> wou'd) hold, their tongues, if treated ſo ſeverely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Equality of Juſtice is that alone which upholds a State, and makes a Kingdom happy.</p>
                  <p>And why muſt there be all this ſtir about the D. when 'tis more than probable he may not ſurvive his Brother, for whoſe long Life, I am perſuaded he, as well as all honeſt Subjects, does heartily pray: But if he ſhould, pray, why, if a Papiſt, muſt he, more than the <hi>French</hi> King, or other Popiſh Princes, deſtroy his Subjects? To do ſo, would be againſt his Intereſt, if a <hi>Turk,</hi> or an Atheiſt.</p>
                  <p>The Caſe wou'd not then be, what it was in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days: Thoſe Laws, by which Men ſuffer'd, (and yet in her Six years there were not Three hundred, and few of them too purely for Religion) are abrogated; the Body of the People were then more Papiſts, than now Proteſtants; and no new Laws can be made, without a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, out of which, as well as out of all Offices, <hi>R. C.</hi> are excluded, by Oaths and Penalties, not in the Princes Power to remit or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give: So that, upon the whole, there is, indeed, on this account, no real danger of any Innovation in Religion; and therefore we may well look on this, but as a Pretence to undermine Monarchy it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>But leſt this ſingle String ſhould fail, they have cunningly found out another for their Bow, <hi>The Inexorableneſs of the D's temper, if once of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended:</hi> A groundleſs and malicious Scandal; an Opinion that being generally ſpread abroad, has already begot many great Evils, and, if continued, will, in all probability, run us into infinite Calamities and Diſorders, not to be equall'd, but by the Malice of the Contrivers: For, his being thus miſrepreſented, muſt needs add to the Peoples ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93949:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> in oppoſing, and his violence in aſſerting, his Right to the Crown: and therefore I wonder why you ſuffer your ſelves to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon, and your Underſtandings ſubjected to that Slavery which is certainly deſigned againſt your Perſons, by the <hi>Ambitious,</hi> without prying into the Grounds, and conſidering the Conſequences of that Calumny. I am ſure, did his Enemies allow but half the time for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, as they do for Paſſion, they would find his R. H. is much leſs fway'd with an inordinate deſire of <hi>Revenge,</hi> than they are with a <hi>falſe and miſguided Zeal;</hi> or, which is more, that he is as void of that <hi>ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Humour,</hi> as they that charge him with it, are of <hi>Candour and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity.</hi> The knowledge of this Truth I owe to my obſervation of his <hi>Temper, Principles,</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> in the many Varieties of his Fortune: But I am now more bold to affirm it, ſince his coming into <hi>Scotland;</hi> becauſe, three days after I had ſhew'd him your Letters, he publickly declared in Council, That tho' the Malice of his Adverſaries might poſſibly deprive him of a Crown, together with the Affections of the People; yet it would never of the Royal Vertue of Clemency: which whether he derives more from the Blood of his Father, or the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Brother, is an undecided Queſtion; as it likewiſe is, whether the one merited more by laying down his Life for his Peoples Liberty, than the other by pardoning ſo many thouſands, who had forfeited theirs to his Juſtice: That he was not ignorant, how <hi>Machiavil</hi>'s Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, of <hi>Eortiter calumniare &amp; aliquid adhaerebit,</hi> was daily put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice by his Adverſaries; nothing being ſo uſual with them, as to traduce his moſt blameleſs Actions, calling Juſtice, Cruelty; Bounty, Prodigality; Reſolution, Obſtinacy; Valour, Raſhneſs; and, in fine, any thing that is Great or Glorious, Baſe and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>generous: Yet he hoped Truth would at laſt prevail againſt his and its own Enemies, and make it as impoſſible for them to ſpread their Calumnies to his diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, as for him to leave any to ſeverity, or puniſhment, that had firſt left their Crimes: That he always look'd upon <hi>Revenge</hi> as <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of a canker'd and impotent Mind, inhumantly rejoycing in the Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Oppreſſed, and as inſatiable in Cruelty, as the memory of receiv'd Injuries is commonly indelible;</hi> than which, nothing was more contrary to his Nature, having, beſides the Commands of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> been taught from his Infancy, That ſo poor and mean a Paſſion ought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to influence a Prince, who is obliged by Honour to end his Wrath, as ſoon as his Enemies do their Malice; and, having no Rivals to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with, is then to be accounted moſt victorious, when he triumphs over himſelf, by conquering his Paſſions: That he challeng'd any that knew him, to give one Inſtance, wherein he had ſwerv'd from this Maxim, or exercis'd any Rigour againſt any Offender, that had truly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93949:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſincerely repented: That it was true, he could not forget the <hi>French</hi> Proverb, <hi>Qui ſe fait un brebis, le Loup le mange,</hi> i. e. <hi>The Wolf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours him that makes himſelf a Sheep;</hi> and therefore would not, by an over-eaſineſs of Nature, yield tamely to his own Ruine, and ſuffer himſelf to be made a Prey to the Ambition and Inſolence of others; but was reſolv'd to temper the Methods of gaining and enjoying his juſt Rights, with a mixture of Severity and Mildneſs, proportionable to the oppoſition he ſhould meet with: And laſtly, That he could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, very well between thoſe whom <hi>Ignorance,</hi> or <hi>Imprudence,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried inſenſibly beyond the bounds of Duty, and thoſe who <hi>knowingly,</hi> and <hi>adviſedly,</hi> ran not onely into <hi>Extremes</hi> themſelves, but likewiſe, by <hi>Lies,</hi> and <hi>falſe Suggeſtions,</hi> hindred many to return from, and drove others to, wicked and malicious <hi>Practices;</hi> and, conſequently, he hop'd, none would wonder if <hi>Theſe</hi> ſhould feel the ſmart of his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> as the <hi>Other</hi> might be ſure, upon diſclaiming their Errours, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd into <hi>Mercy;</hi> being perſuaded, that puniſhing ſuch Men could no more be termed <hi>Revenge,</hi> than executing the Laws againſt <hi>Traytors,</hi> and <hi>Diſturbers of the Publick Quiet,</hi> could reaſonably be accounted <hi>Cruelty:</hi> But leſt, upon this ſcore, he ſhould be thought to reſerve a Latitude to himſelf of wreaking his Anger againſt any, at pleaſure, he was willing to give all the Aſſurances they themſelves could expect, and would move his Brother to agree to an Act of Parliament for that purpoſe; that he would freely forgive, and bury in eternal Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, whatever is paſt, that ſo either all may be throughly recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, or ſuch as are guilty of that <hi>Implacability</hi> which they attribute to him, differenced from the reſt, and left without excuſe, to the terror of their own evil Conſciences, and his juſt Reſentments.</p>
                  <p>I cannot imagine what further can reaſonably be expected from an injur'd Prince, and am confident, whoever after continues diſſatisfied, is as great an Enemy to Reaſon, as he is to his R. H. and in ſtead of <hi>taking away,</hi> ſeeks to <hi>perpetuate</hi> your Differences. Nor do I ſee why any, before him, ſhould be credited in an Affair of this Importance; ſince all acknowledge him to be of a frank and generous Nature, free from all Diſſimulation, and the little Politick Fetches and Evaſions which ſerve other Mens turn to break their Promiſes: Whereas the Ringleaders of his Adverſaries are vers'd in all the Arts and Wiles of forming Parties and Factions, and conſequently, cannot be thought to ſtick at forging any Lie, or Aſperſion, beneficial to the End they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. But, allowing an equal probability of truth in his Denial, and their Charge; <hi>yet to erre of his ſide, is not leſs ſafe, and I am ſure much more honeſt and honourable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis indeed the uſual Cheat of aſpiring Men, by ſpecious Pretences
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93949:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> firſt to engage the unwary in their Conſpiracies, and, when either Fear or Honeſty opens their Eyes, then to make them believe, they are ſo far advanced, that they cannot with ſafety retire; and that the State or Perſon they provok'd, will admit of no other Attonement than that of their Lives and Fortunes. This Device (to omit ancienter Times) in <hi>Philip</hi> the Second's Reign, fill'd the <hi>Belgick</hi> Plains with the Blood of his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Subjects; brought <hi>France,</hi> ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, under ſeveral Kings, almoſt to a total deſtruction; depriv'd our late Sovereign of his Life, and Crown, which I am confident was not by the major part firſt intended, in 1640; and had like to have kept his preſent Majeſty in perpetual Exile, had not Providence wrought Miracles in his favour, and, in ſpite of all the Artifices of his Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Subjects, reſtored him to his Throne, without Blood or Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: among which, I cannot but remember that deviliſh Pamphler, intituled, <hi>A Letter from Bruxelles, &amp;c.</hi> mention'd in <hi>Baker</hi>'s Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, publiſh'd after his Majeſties Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> inſinuating; That notwithſtanding his Promiſes, if they ſuffer'd his Return, he would with all imaginable Cruelty revenge the <hi>Death of his Father,</hi> and not forget it to the third Generation of thoſe concerned in that horrid <hi>Murder.</hi> This put the People into a great Conſternation; yet his unparallell'd <hi>Clemency,</hi> and his ſo often preſſing his Parliament to paſs the <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> ſufficiently prov'd the Malice of that Invention. But I hope this <hi>Cheat</hi> is now ſo well known, that it will gain no Credit with conſidering Perſons: I onely wiſh ſome care were taken to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the weak and unthinking, that Peace and Unity, which ſeem to have parted from you with his R. H. might with him be once more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd, and the happy <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of both Kingdoms be made <hi>perpetual,</hi> by ſuffering no <hi>rent</hi> or gap in the Royal Line; which all of our <hi>Nation,</hi> (and we hear thoſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> will not be leſs forward) are not onely oblig'd, but have vow'd to maintain, with the hazard of their Lives and Fortunes: a Neceſſity we hope you will never put upon us, as well for your own ſakes, as for the Peace and Quiet of this Kingdom, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he has not the leaſt Concern, who is, and always will be,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, &amp;c.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <head>POST SCRIPT.</head>
                     <p>JUſt now I hear of a new Project ſet on foot, to give the King 600000 <hi>l.</hi> of which he may diſpoſe one at pleaſure, on condition he will conſent to the Bill of Excluſion; and that, in return, he ſhall have Power, by Act of Parliament, in caſe he have no Iſſue by his Queen, to ſettle, by Will, the Crown upon any of his Natural Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. To manage this Deſign, a new Set of Miniſters is contriv'd: A
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93949:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> great Lord, whoſe Son moſt, if not wholly, influences the Houſe of Commons, is to be made a Duke; another Earl, to be Treaſurer; Sir <hi>W. J.</hi> is to be L. C. J. Col. <hi>T.</hi> to be a Secretary of State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I am very ſorry to perceive the Differences between the King and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, are fomented by Perſons of the ſame Humour with thoſe in 1640. who, meeting at Sir <hi>Robert Long</hi>'s, undertook, if his then Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty would do ſo and ſo, he ſhould govern the Parliament to all Intents and Purpoſes: The King conſenting to every, excepting one, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd Preferments, was refus'd, crying out, <hi>One and all,</hi> having before bound themſelves accordingly. One of the then leading Men has in this Parliament a Son, whoſe Power and Ambition falls very little ſhort, if at all, of his Fathers; and if you have a mind to diſcover <hi>Hercules</hi> his Proportion by that of his Foot, compare the <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and the late <hi>Addreſs,</hi> and, without naming, you will find the near Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Authors. For ſhame, let not ſuch Proceedings <hi>be nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam'd, doing your Country Service.</hi> I remember to have heard, that in the ſhort Parliament, before that of (40.) when ſome more zealous, than wiſe, Members ſpake too extravagantly, a ſober Gentleman, and no Courtier, ſtood up, and ſaid, <hi>he was for more moderate Counſels, leſt their preſent heat and exorbitance ſhould put that King, and his Succeſſors, for ever out of conceit with Parliaments, who depended upon his Pleaſure.</hi> I wiſh the whole Kingdom, as well as their Prince, may have no reaſon to grow weary of, and diſlike the ſetled Conſtitution of Commons in Parliament, chuſing rather to have, as formerly, the whole Power in the King, and his Great Council of Lords and Barons. <hi>Extremes are near one another; and many, by graſping at too much, have loſt the little they enjoy'd:</hi> This is as fooliſh, as with the Dog, in the Apologue, to loſe the Subſtance for the Shadow: And ſince Prudence tells us, <hi>A long provok'd and incens'd Clemency turns into the greateſt Cruelty,</hi> you ought to bridle your Paſſions and Ambition, leſt you too late repent your Madneſs and your Folly. This Conſideration has carried me beyond the uſual length of a <hi>Poſt ſcript,</hi> wherein I deſign'd to have ſaid little more, than that I underſtand, the D. writes this night to the King his Brother, <hi>That if he can be ſecure his Parliament will agree with him upon quitting his Intereſt, that he ſhould not longer ſtruggle for him, who would not onely hazard his uncertain hopes of a Crown, but would with joy expoſe his Life, to do his Majeſty ſervice; whoſe long Reign, and Happineſs, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Forgeries of his Enemies, he as heartily wiſhes, as any other the moſt Loyal Subject in his Dominions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Conſider the Greatneſs of this Generoſity, and let not Malice for ever prevail, to the defamation of Innocence, and the diſturbance, if not the ruine, of theſe Nations.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:93949:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93949:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
